Slim Ouertani June-81, Tunisian

ouertani@gmail.com • (00966)-(0)-583012381 • Riyadh (Saudi Arabia) linkedin.com/in/ouertani • ouertani.github.io • jroller.com/ouertani • twitter.com/ouertani

Architect, InfoQ Fr Editor, Cloud & SOA Trainer Togaf, Archimate, PMP, SOA, Cloud, Spring, Java, Cmmi, ITIL, Mongo, Scala

Summary

tor, Cloud and SOA trainer, founder and organizer of Riyadh IT Architecture Meetup. After his bachelor's degree in computer science, Slim spent over than 10 years in multinational companies such as Orange, Sagem and STMicroelectronics as architect, international agile coach and Head of IT development department. His main role was to build, design and collaborate in the development of enterprise solutions.

Slim regularly contributes to InfoQ-FR community where he is the author of many articles and news. you to follow him on twitter @ouertani.

Slim Ouertani is solution architect, InfoQ-Fr edi- He's broad certified as in addition to his SOA and Cloud certifications: Trainer & Architect, Slim holds multiple certifications including Togaf 9, Archimate 2, PMP, ITIL, CMMi, Mongo, Spring, JAVA, SCALA and reactive programming...

Trained as an architect, Slim specializes in enterprise Java development, functional programming focusing on highly scalable applications and now expanding his experience to cloud computing.

Slim enjoys open source contribution and invite

Experience

Al-Elm Information Security

Solution Architect

RIYADH, SAUDI ARABIA

06-2014 – present

- Member/Founder of ELM Development Architecture Center of Excellence.
- EPG committee member, responsible of the architecture models, oversee the process architecture, approve it and ensuring the process improvement.
- Architecting and Designing enterprise solutions using diverse technology stack
 Work with peers to conduct Solution Architecture Reviews for a broad set of projects
- Review and provide input into functional & non-functional requirements
- Provide consulting and conduct reviews through the development lifecycle
- Defining the Architecture and guiding the use of various tools, technologies and techniques in the realization of that Architecture
- Create and maintain a set of standard practices, patterns and anti-patterns and ensure the appropriate usage of that.

Sofrecom (Orange FT Group)

Tunis, Tunisia 03-2013 - 06-2014

Software Architect, International Agile Coach Manage and direct virtual distributed teams

Make or Buy Analysis

- Establish regular meetings to review technical designs and provide mentoring and guidance
- Mentor development teams on different architecture and design paradigms or practices
- Maintain a knowledge base of emerging technologies and products
 Scrum Master, Enterprise Architect, Apache Camel, Spring
 CXF, Spring Batch, Atomikos, ActiveMq, Jonas, hibernate

Zenika

Paris, FRANCE

12-2012 - 03-2013

JEE Architect

• Client: Bouygues Telecom

- Project: Home Automation (2 months)
- BBox embedded automation solution communicating with centralized system
 - Embedded: OSGI, REST server/client, Raspberry pi
 - Server: Fuse ESB, CXF, Camel, Spring, Jax-Rs, Osgi, Maven
- Client : SwissPost Project : Image Plus (2 months)
- Online outsourcing solution for picture processing.
 - Scrum, Kanban, Jenkies, Git, Cloudbees, Maven
 - MVP, Spring 3.1, GWT 2.5, JPA 2

Orange

Tunis, Tunisia

JEE 6, MDB, JPA, Scala, Wicket, Play, J2ME, Spring ROO, WS, Glassfish, Talend, Birt

01-2010 - 11-2012

- Development and implementation of a web service platform :

JEE 6, SCALA, EJB 3.1, JAX-WS, Oracle, JPA
 IN/AIR, BSCS/CMS/Data Charging/CRM/IVR/USSD

- Development of the "after sales service" solution: Play 1.2.x, groovy, jquery
- Launch of BI project: Talend, Birt, Oracle Bulk SMS: Wicket, JEE 6, JPA, Postgres Unbarring SMS: J2ME, JAX-WS, MDB, JPA

- Different applications: inter systems and synchronization platforms, web application...

Sagem Software & Technologies

Tunis, Tunisia 06-2009 - 01-2010

Solution Architect

Architecture design and integration of a communication server and administration of remote

- JEE, JMS, Spring, GWT, AndroMda, Hibernate, SMSJboss, ActiveMq, MDA

Solution Architect

03-2008 - 06-2009

- Modular OSGi Server architecture under Linux platform responsible for controlling and interacting with electricity counters in order to retrieve statistics and have data storing/manipulation via different technologies and frameworks
 - OSGI, SCA, Spring DM, JAX-WS, JPA, GPRS, GSM/DATA, SMS, SNMP4j, Hessian, Ftp, Equinox, JETTY, POSTGREŠQL
 - DISTRIBUTED COMPUTING, Cryptography

Solution Architect & Team Leader

12-2007 - 03-2008

- Designing an SOA architecture and implementation of an Intranet service for human resources using liferay portal.

 - JEE5, EJB3, JAX-WS, JSF, PORTLET, JPA, SOA
 GLASSFISH V2, TOMCAT6, LIFERAY 4.4, POSTGRESQL

STMicroelectronics Tunis, Tunisia 02-2006 - 12-2007Coordinator

- Implementing Intranet tools used for monitoring the evolution of validation campaigns.
 - J2EE, JSF, Hibernate/JPA, JAXB/JAXP, Design Pattern
 - TOMCAT 5.5, POSTGRESQL

Developer

12-2005 - 02-2006

- Validating processors and compilers under different platforms.
 - Linux, Solaris, Cygwin, Mingwin, Perl ,Shell

GL TRADE

Tunis, Tunisia

Developer & designer

08-2005 - 12-2005

- GL TACTICS: A trader module enhancing the efficiency of the negotiating teams giving them the possibility to customize the implementation strategies and accelerate the decision process.
 - C++, Design Pattern

Please refer to my Linked-in profile for a more complete list of work experiences along with recommendations.

Certificate

Archimate Certified, Open Group	Score 82%, 02-2016
Archimate Foundation, Open Group	Score 97%, 02-2016
Cloud Trainer, Arcitura	10-2015
Cloud Architect, Arcitura	With Honors, 10-2015
Cloud Professional, Arcitura	With Honors, 09-2015
Togaf Certified, Open Group	Score 90%, 06-2015
ITIL Foundation, Exin	Score 95%, 06-2015
Togaf Foundation, Open Group	Score 95%, 04-2015
Project Management Professional, PMI	03-2015
SOA Trainer, Arcitura	01-2015
SOA Architect, Arcitura	With Honors, 12-2014
SOA Professional, Arcitura	With Honors, 11 -2 014
Introduction to Cmmi for development, Cmmi Institute	09-2014

Entrepreneurship for all, EFFECTUATION, EMLYON	Score 75,8%, 01-2014
Principles of Reactive Programming, Coursera	Score 97.5%, 01-2014
MongoDB for DBAs, MongoDB	Score 94%, 11 -2 013
MongoDb for java, MongoDb	Score 95%, 10-2013
Spring Framework 3, Pivotal	Score 94%, 02-2013
Java 6 Programmer Certified Professional, Oracle	Score 100%, 08-2012
Team Performance, STMicroelectronics	04-2007
English, British Council	4B, 02-2007
GL Certified Professional, GL TRADE	09-2005

Education

National School of Computer ScienceENSI Graduation Project in Computer Engineering	Tunis,Tunisia 2005
National School of Computer ScienceENSI Bachelor Degree in Computer Science	Tunis, Tunisia 2002 – 2005
Tunis Preparatory Institute for Engineering StudiesIPEIT Preparatory Courses (Math Sup, Math Spe)	Tunis, Tunisia 2000 – 2002
Hannibal (Pre-university Secondary Education)	Ariana, Tunisia 1994 – 2000

Other Activities

InfoQ Fr Editor

http://www.infoq.com/fr/author/Slim-Ouertani

BLOGGGING

http://java.dzone.com/users/slim.ouertani

http://ouertani.github.io

http://www.jroller.com/ouertani

http://twitter.com/ouertani

MAGAZINE

From Microservices to SOA - 20.07.2015 Service Technology Magazine - Issue XCI http://servicetechmag.com/I91/0715-1

OPEN SOURCE

https://github.com/ouertani http://www.reactive-streams.org

Founder & Organizer

Riyadh IT Architecture Meetup

http://www.meetup.com/Riyadh-IT-Architecture

INTERVIEW

Paremus, SCA with OSGI, David Savage

http://www.prosyst.com/

07.02.2009

http://goo.gl/H5yJzY

STAMPLE

https://stample.co Scala, Akka, Play

ElasticSearch, MongoDb, Amazon S3, GreenCloud

p. 4

Computer Skills

Design Functional programming, EA, UML, Design Pattern, MVC, MDA, OO, MVP

Architecture Microservices, Reactive, N-tiers, SOA, SCA, Actor

Cloud CloudBees, Heroku, App Engine, Amazon S3, GreenCloud

Agile Scrum, Kanban

Web Service Metro, JAX-WS,CXF,JAX-RS,Hessian, Rest, Axis SCALA, Java/JEE/OSGI, C/C++/C#, ADA, COBOL,...

Web PLAY, GWT, Vert.x, WICKET, JSF, PORTLET, JSP, SERVLET, APPLET, HTML

XML, XSL, XSD, JAXP, JAXB, Stax, SAX, DOM, SCALA XML

<u>Database</u> PostgresSQL, MySQL, Oracle, MongoDb <u>Persistence</u> JPA, Hibernate, Toplink, EclipseLink, Slick

Containers Glassfish V3, Tomcat 5/6/7, Equinox, JBOSS AS, Jonas 4, OC4J

Framework Spring, Spring DM, Liferay 4.4, Fuse ESB, Camel, Spring Batch, ElasticSearch

OS UNIX/LINUX, Mac OS, Windows XP, Windows NT, SOLARIS

<u>IDE</u> Netbeans, Eclipse, Idea, JDeveloper 10g

Management IceScrum, Bugzilla, Trello

<u>Build tools</u> Gradle, Maven, Sbt, Javac, Scalac, Ant Version controlGit, Subversion, Perforce, CVS, Jazz

Collaboration Trello, Slack, Github, Codex, Wiki, Sharepoint

Training

Project Management Professional, PMP	11.2014
OSGi design pattern: White board & Extender	08.2009
By: Slim Ouertani	
SCA architecture with Newton	01.2009
By: David Savage & Mike Francis	
OSGi, architecture and environment	05.2008
By: Roman Roelofsen	

Publications

Pour le fun: for-comprehension à la sauce Java 8	23.07.2015
Vrais ou Faux Jumeaux ?	25.11.2014
Curryfication Java: methods & fonctions	29.07.2014
Des Lenses en Java ?	30.06.2014
Barboter dans le compilateur Java	02.06.2014
Mon Trampoline avec Java 8	18.04.2014
Démystifier les iteratees avec Java	01.11.2013
Le Trio: Akka, Spring et Scala	16.10.2013
Rest with Scala and Vert.x	18.02.2013
Fun with Scala and Vert.x	11.02.2013
Getting Started with Play 2.1, Scala 2.10 and Slick 0.11.1	01.11.2012

Please refer to my Linked-in profile for a more complete list of publications since 2008.

News

MongoDB: la magie des Reactive-Streams avec les Capped Collections	21.05.2015
Publication de l'API Reactive Streams 1.0	07.05.2015
Docker, le dernier clou dans le cercueil des serveurs d'applications Java?	19.03.2015

Languages